ILGWU General Executive Board Minutes on Microfilm 5780/016 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU General Executive Board Minutes on Microfilm
1900-1975
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/016 mf
5.5 cubic feet
18 microfilm reels
Minutes, Microfilm
Includes the minutes and reports of the General Executive Board of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
5490737
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
March 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, March 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Scope and Contents
Includes the minutes and reports of the General Executive Board of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU Records
5780/016. ILGWU. General Executive Board minutes
5780/018. ILGWU. General Executive Board. Appeal Committee cases
5780/189. ILGWU. Perry Parker papers
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. General Executive Board
5490737
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1900-1917 (Reel 1)
  Scope and Contents
  June 3, 1900 - February 16, 1917. 883 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1917-1924 (Reel 2)
  March 14, 1917 - May 26, 1924. 1386 images. 2 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1924-1929 (Reel 3)
  August 25, 1924 - October 29, 1929. 1084 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1929-1938 (Reel 4)
  December 13, 1929 - May 3, 1938. 1372 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1938-1940 (Reel 5)
  May 23, 1938 - November 21, 1940. 1372 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1940-1945 (Reel 6)
  December 20, 1940 - March 8, 1945. 1179 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1945-1947 (Reel 7)
  April 23, 1945 - June 27, 1947. 1033 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1947-1950 (Reel 8)
  September 2, 1947 - May 16, 1950. 1152 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1950-1954 (Reel 9)
  June 2, 1950 - May 25, 1954. 1297 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1954-1958 (Reel 10)
  September 14, 1954 - February 11, 1958. 1108 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1958-1961 (Reel 11)
  May 12, 1958 - May 3, 1961. 1402 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1961-1963 (Reel 12)
  June 19, 1961 - September 9, 1963. 1238 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1963-1966 (Reel 13)
  November 15, 1963 - June 21, 1966. 1260 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1966-1967 (Reel 14)
  September 5, 1966 - September 29, 1967. 1355 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1967-1969 (Reel 15)
  December 14, 1967 - May 12, 1969. 1153 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1969-1971 (Reel 16)
  August 12, 1969 - September 16, 1971. 1026 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1970-1973 (Reel 17)
  August 26, 1970; October 26-29, 1970; November 29, 1971 - February 27, 1973. 1324 images. 3 copies.
- Executive Board Minutes. General., 1973-1975 (Reel 18)
  May 24, 1973 - October 8, 1975. 1382 images. 3 copies.